[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Two]
[第二集]
Brothers have to go to work now.
哥哥们得去干活了
I can't play with you this time.
这回就不陪你玩了
Next time?
下回啊
Let's go.
走吧
Goodbye Aunt.
姨妈再见
Wait a minute. Wait a minute.
等会儿 等会儿
Come.
来
Take all the buns.
把包子都拿上
Brother, you promised to give me a grasshopper!
哥哥 你答应过我要送我蝈蝈的
I'll keep my promise!
哥哥答应你的一定做到
Come home if you need to.
有事回家啊
Thank you Aunt.
谢谢姨妈
[Songshan Road, French Concession, Shanghai]
[上海法租界嵩山路]
Pear paste pastries... sweet and savoury,
梨膏糖呀嘛 甜津津
a mouthful of delight!
吃在嘴里美在心
The song goes:
唱的是
[Chen Henian, youngest son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈鹤年 陈独秀幼子]
Xiao Fangqing in the Pearl Tower
珍珠塔里的小方卿
is so happy to meet
欢喜上了
Xiao Qingqing in "The Legend of the White Snake".
"白蛇传" 里小青青
Xiao Fangqing
小方卿呀嘛小青青
is so happy
今朝真开心
to the movies with her.
约好一道去看电影
Hey! Selling pear pastries!
哎 卖梨膏糖了
Good, stop!
好嘞
Mr Menzou is here!
孟邹先生来了
[Wang Mengzou, Manager of Yadong Library]
[汪孟邹 亚东图书馆经理]
Menzou!
孟邹
Junman!
君曼
I've brought you Zhong Fu back from the dock!
我把仲甫从码头上给你接回来了
Where?
人呢
At the back!
后边
Look!
看
Zimei! Henian! Look who's back!
子美 鹤年 看看谁回来了
It's Dad! Call Dad!
是爸爸 叫爸爸
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhong Fu, famous revolutionary]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 著名革命家]
Why don't you have an umbrella?
怎么不打伞
Zimei! Henian!
子美 鹤年
Qiaonian? Yannian? Where are they?
乔年 延年呢
Let's go home first.
先回家再说吧
Okay, go, go, go.
好 走 走 走
Let's go home!
咱们回家喽
Thank you, Menzou.
辛苦了 孟邹
Go, go, go!
走 走 走
What are you doing?
你干吗呢
What are you doing out in the rain?
你在外边淋雨干什么
Tasting the Jiangnan rain.
感受一下江南的雨
Quick, quick, quick!
快快快
Were you that stupid in Japan?
你在日本是不待傻了你
Look at the rain on you!
你瞧你淋的这一身雨
There's raindrops all over!
全是雨滴
What's a drop of rain?
一身雨算什么呀
When I was in Japan,
我在日本的时候
I was covered in lice.
还一身的虱子呢
Once.
有一次
Then Zhang Shizhao asked me to edit an issue.
那章士钊让我赶编一期稿子
I locked myself in my room,
我把自己憋在房间里
I didn't leave the house for half a month.
足不出户半个月
Then the article was finished.
后来稿子写完了
I went out,
我走出来
Yi Baisha looked at me and said:
易白沙看着我说
What are those spots on your body?
你身上斑斑点点的是什么呀
I looked down and it was all...
我低头一看这全是
Don't say, don't say, don't say.
你别说别说别说
Mr Chen.
陈先生
You've suffered.
你受苦了
Come. Sit.
过来 坐
Sit with me and listen to the rain for a while.
陪我坐下听会儿雨
There is no revolution without suffering,
干革命哪有不苦的
but I brought this misery upon myself.
可这苦是我自找的
I like to... I like to enjoy it.
我情愿的 乐在其中
It's just that... I got you into trouble.
只是 我把你连累了
You're a talented student from Beijing Normal University,
你是北女师的高才生
suffering with me.
跟着我一起受罪
I'm sorry.
对不起
As long as the family can be together,
只要一家人能团聚
whatever the suffering and hardship,
受多少罪吃多少苦
I'm not afraid.
我都不怕
It's just that Yannian and Qiaonian don't want to go home.
只是延年和乔年不愿意回家
I don't feel well.
我心里憋屈
Zhong Fu.
仲甫
Why don't you go and get the two children tomorrow
要不你明天去把两个孩子
and bring them home?
接到家里来吧
Don't let them roam around outside.
别让他们在外边游荡了
I'm not going to pick them up.
我不去接他们
These two boys have a lot of backbone.
这两个小子挺有骨气
It's good to go out and make your own living.
出去闯荡 自食其力挺好的
Yannian and Qiaonian
延年和乔年
are two good boys with big ambitions.
是两个心存大志的好孩子
After the May 9th National Disgrace,
五九国耻之后
they both came to Shanghai to study.
他们俩跑到上海来求学
Seeing our family's difficulties,
见我们家境困难
they had brought from the countryside
楞是把从乡下
100 silver yuan for tuition
带过来的一百大洋的学费
and gave it to me.
塞给了我
They went out to work on their own.
自己跑出去打工
I tried to give it back to them
我怎么还给他们
but they wouldn't listen.
怎么劝都不听
You said Shanghai docks are so rough.
你说上海滩这么险恶
What would happen if something happened to them?
他们俩要是出点什么事可怎么办
Zhong Fu.
仲甫
I'm begging you.
算我求你了
You go and bring them both home.
你去把他们俩接回家来吧
Junman.
君曼
When I was abroad,
我在国外
I heard a song from Europe
听过欧洲的一首歌曲
called "The Internationale".
名字叫 《国际歌》
Although the lyrics have not been translated into Chinese,
虽然歌词还没有翻译成中文
there are a few lines in it
但其中有几句
I was very impressed by.
倒是让我印象很深
The idea is
大意是
there is no saviour
世上没有救世主
or there is no fairy god.
也没有神仙上帝
To create happiness for all
要创造大家的幸福
is up to us.
只有靠我们自己
Well sung... well said.
唱得好 说得对
From large countries to small individuals,
大到国家 小到个体
one should forge their own destiny.
自己的命运自己争取
Trusting your life
把自己的命远
to your father and family.
寡托到老子和家庭身上
You can't rely on that.
那是靠不住的
So, what is the job of the father?
那 你这个父亲是于什么的
Where has your duty as a father gone?
你父亲的责任到哪儿去了
It is my duty
我的责任就是
to let them know
要让他们知道
how to be live up to
怎么才能担得起
the social and historical responsibilities of this country.
这个国家社会和历史的责任
In these troubled times,
如今乱世
to be a son of I, Chen Duxiu,
做我陈独秀的儿子
one must first work hard on one's heart and soul.
必先苦其心志劳其筋骨
Starve the body and the skin, but not the soul.
饿其体肤 空乏其身
Act in accordance with the law,
行拂乱其所为
so your heart is willing
所以动心忍性
to endure what it once could not.
曾益其所不能
You are a thinker against the ways of Confucius and Mencius.
你这个反对孔孟之道的斗士
Why did you make a statement
怎么倒把孟夫子的语录
out of Mencius' quotes?
做成教条啦
Yuan Shikai wants to make Confucianism the state religion,
袁世凯要把孔教当国教
of course I want to oppose it.
我当然要反了
But make no mistake,
但是你不要弄错
I am against
我反的是那些
the three principles of Confucianism that are poisoning the people.
毒害人民的孔教三纲
Neither Confucius nor Mencius.
并不是孔夫子和孟夫子
All right, all right, I can't talk you out of it.
行了行了 我说不过你
Step inside.
走进屋吧
It's cold.
好冷啊
Let's go.
走
[Yadong Library]
[亚东图书馆]
Brother.
哥
That thing, put it in the jar.
那个东西把它放罐里
Is it fine?
没事儿吧
It's fine.
没事
You're all set, right?
你都准备了吧
There is no point in playing chess. Put it back.
行棋无悔啊 放回去
Ready to go Huangshan, Maofeng?
准备好了 黄山毛峰
Zhong Fu!
仲甫
Brother Zhong Fu!
仲甫兄
Put it here.
放这儿吧
Come on, come on, we're waiting for you.
来快来 就等你了
Zhong Fu, ladies and gentlemen!
仲甫 各位
Everyone's here!
都到了
Brother Zhong Fu, we're all waiting for you!
仲甫老弟 就等你们了
Zishou.
子寿
Zipei.
子沛
[Yi Baisha, styled Yue Cun, scholar of the New Culture movement]
[易白沙 字 越邨 新文化运动学者]
Zhong Fu.
仲甫
Baisha.
白沙
Yongcheng.
永成
[Zou Yongcheng, styled Qi Zhi]
[邹永成 字 器之]
Since we left the boat, I've missed you.
船上一别 很想念
Greetings, gentlemen.
各位先生好
Come on, you're barging in.
快 你们驳来了
Go and meet us at the front!
快去前面见见呀
No, I'm not going to meet him.
不去 我才不去见他呢
Why is this child so stubborn?
这孩子 咋这么犟呢
You tell me, he's still your old man,
你说呀 他是你们老子
then the bones are still attached to the tendons.
那打断了 骨头还连着筋呢
Where did all the hate come from?
哪来这么大仇恨
I don't have a grudge against him,
我跟他没仇
but I just don't go to see him.
但我就是不去见他
Same temper as your father.
跟你爹呀一个脾气
I'm sure of it.
认准的理啊
I can't get it back with nine oxen.
九头牛都拉不回来
The fire is good.
火候不错
Why are you, Wang Menzou,
你说你这个汪孟邹
so stingy?
怎那么抠门啊
I'm invited to dinner,
给我接风请我吃饭
not at a restaurant, but at a home.
不下馆子 在自家里弄
How much money do you save?
能省多少钱呀
He said it! I do save money.
他说的 我省钱
What would you like to eat?
你想吃的东西
I prepared it all yesterday.
昨天我都准备好了
The cook was also taken from Zishou's house.
这大厨还是在子寿家里请来的
I didn't spend any mony on this.
这些 我不花钱哪
I can attest.
这我可做证啊
What Menzou said is true in every sense of the word.
孟邹说的是句句属实
[Chen Zishou, owner of Qunyi Book Club] Our family cook
[陈子寿 群益书社老板]
Zhong Fu, I'm borrowing the cook's skills.
仲甫 就赁着借厨子这份情
You should also write us a couple of words.
你也应该给我们写两幅字吧
To each his own.
一码归一码
He gave me a reception
他给我接风
by borrowing the cook from you.
从你那儿借厨子
He should be grateful to you.
应该他领你的情啊
What's it to do with me?
跟我有什么关系呀
Me!
我
Zhong Fu, who is the stingy one?
仲甫 到底谁抠门啊
Of course, he's stingy one!
当然是他抠门了
And the famous Yadong Library
还有 亚东图书馆鼎鼎大名
has always been housed in this alley.
就一直蜗居在这个弄堂里
I've tried so many times to get him to move out
我劝了他多少次要搬出去
but he won't listen!
他就是不听啊
It's easy to move out!
搬出去 那么容易呀
Wang Mengzou, I tell you,
汪孟邹我告诉你
we are doing great things with a bang.
我们是轰轰烈烈做大事业的
If you want to die,
要想死
just cower in the alleyway.
你只管缩在弄堂里
If you want to live,
要想活
you have to move out of the alleyway
你就要搬出弄堂
and onto the main road.
上大马路
All right, all right.
行行行
You're standing around talking,
你站着说话不腰疼
then sit down and talk.
那你坐下说
Everyone sit down.
大家都坐
Sit down, sit down.
坐坐坐
[Chen Qiaonian, second son of Chen Duxiu] Qiaonian.
[陈乔年 陈独秀次子] 乔年
You're too young to hold a grudge.
你年纪小不记仇
This is a lotus leaf and yellow beef feet dish.
一会儿把这道荷叶黄牛蹄
Serve it to your father.
给你爹端上去
Meet him.
跟他见个面
Give him a surprise.
给他个惊喜
OK, I'll send him up later
行一会儿我给他送上去
and surprise him.
让他惊喜惊喜
[Chen Yannian, eldest son of Chen Duxiu] That's right!
[陈延年 陈独秀长子]
Today, everyone invited to
今天呢 请大家来
firstly
一是呢
celebrate Zhong Fu's return to the country.
为仲甫老弟的回国接风洗尘
That's the second.
这个二一个呀
Since the failure of the Second Revolution,
自打二次革命失败以后
We revolutionaries
我们这些革命党人呢
have been scattered to the winds.
就作鸟兽散了
We went our separate ways and hid into hiding.
是各奔东西 东躲西藏
Some died, some were wounded.
死的死 是伤的伤
Today, having us all here together
今天呢 大家能够聚到一起
after the disaster
那也是劫后余生
is not easy.
实属不易呀
The situation now
现在这个局势呢
is that European powers are at war.
欧洲列强在打仗
Originally it was our country's
本来是我们国家
time to take a break.
得以喘息的一个好的时机
But what about the Japanese?
可这日本人呢
They took advantage of the situation,
他乘虚而入
by proposing
又提出了
the Twenty-One Demands of powers in Shandong.
割让山东势力的二十一条
That Yuan Shikai,
那袁世凯呀
betrayed the country with the National Humiliation of May 9th.
是卖国求荣 五九国耻啊
A disgrace. It is truly a disgrace.
耻辱啊 这真是耻辱啊
[Chen Zipei, Owner of Qunyi Book Club]
[陈子沛 群益书社老板]
And now the entire country is seething,
现在是全国沸腾
protesting.
全国抗争
At this time, what should we do?
这时候 我们怎么办呢
Observe with a critical eye?
冷眼旁观
Be docile subjects? Be a conquered people?
当顺民 当亡国奴
Never.
绝不能
Now is the time for us to fan the flames
现在正需要我们去添把柴
add fuel to the fire.
加个油的时候
So please let us confide in each other,
所以请大家来交交心
what thoughts we have,
大家有什么想法
and all express our own views.
各抒己见吧
Yongcheng is a military man.
永成是一介武夫啊
But I think the most important thing in China today
但我以为 当今中国之要务
is to first defeat Yuan Shikai,
首先是要打倒袁世凯
then create a republic.
再造共和国
Mengzou is right.
孟邹刚才说得对
The Western European powers fighting amongst themselves
西方欧洲列强啊战事混沌
have no time to attend to us.
无暇顾及我们
But Yuan Shikai
袁世凯啊
has no time to encircle and suppress the KMT.
没时间围剿革命党
We need to use this opportunity
我们要趁着这个好时机
to mobilize the masses
发动民众
forment anti-Yuan Shikai public opinion
大造反袁舆论
and actively prepare for hostilities against him.
积极准备反袁战事
When the time is right
一旦时机成熟
we will rise in rebellion
我们就揭等而起
defeat Yuan Shikai in one fell swoop
一举打垮袁世凯
and create a new republic.
再造一个崭新的共和国
General Zou said it well.
邹将军说得好
I was also inspired by Brother Zhong Fu.
我也是啊 受仲甫兄的启发
This time
这次啊
prepare to organize Hunan personnel in Shanghai
准备组织在沪的湘籍人士
set up a national salvation newspaper
办一份救亡报
and mobilize anti-Yuan Shikai sentiments.
大造反袁的舆论
By the way, all esteemed persons present
对了 各位在座的高人
please give us your advice
可得多多指教啊
and lend your guidance.
赐稿提携啊得
For a general to organize a newspaper commends admiration.
邹将军武人办报 令人钦佩
My brothers have been long involved in publishing.
我兄弟搞出版多年
In the future
今后大家
if you have any use for us
如果有用得着我们的地方
we are yours to command.
尽管吩咐
We will do our best to help.
我们全力相帮
Mr Zhang Shizhao has already decided
章士钊先生已经决定
to return to China from Japan.
从日本回国了
I, Mr. Zhang and Zhong Fu
我 章先生还有仲甫
as well as the magazine "The Tiger" we operated
我们经略的《甲寅》杂志
will also return to Shanghai from Japan.
也决定从日本迁回上海
Now that this Hunan-Anhui alliance has been settled
现在这湘皖联手已成定局
I believe that
我相信啊
with the leadership of
在章先生和仲甫
Mr. Zhang and Zhong Fu
这两只领头羊的带领下
we will definitely
我们一定会把报纸办得
make the newspaper a booming success.
轰轰烈烈 惊天动地
Zhong Fu, don't just eat peanuts!
仲甫 你别顾着就吃花生啊
We have been waiting and waiting
这个于盼万盼的
for you to finally come back.
好不容易把你给盼回来了
Everyone wants to hear if you have any opinions
大家都想听听你有什么想法
or new thoughts.
有什么新的思路
Say something.
说说啊
Yes.
是啊
Right, Zhong Fu.
对呀仲甫
The thirteenth year of Emperor Tongzhi's reign,
同治十三年
in a discussion about naval defense, Li Hongzhang
皖人李鸿章在筹议海防折中
termed our China to be
称我中华已处于
at the most critical moment in 3000 years
三千年未遇之大变局
facing the greatest enemy in 3000 years.
三千年未遇之大强敌的时代
I would like to ask everyone present
我想问问诸位
what they think this crisis and this enemy
这个变局和强敌
refers to.
指的是什么
This... What is it?
这个 是什么
Since the twelfth year of Emperor Daoguang
自道光二十年
when Lin Zexu sold opium
林则徐销鸦片
and the British used gunboat diplomacy
英吉利人用坚船利炮
to force open China
打开了中国的大门
our country
我们这国家
has been in crisis.
就已经在大变局了
Li Hongzhang meticulously pursued Westernization, built a navy,
李鸿章精心办洋务 建海军
spent decades busily self-strengthening
忙忙碌碌几十年自救自强
And the result?
结果呢
The Sino-Japanese War. The country collapsed after a single fight
甲午年一战崩溃
helping to achieve the aims of the Japanese empire
成全了一个日本帝国
From then on
从那个时候起
the Qing dynasty has existed only in name.
大清王朝就已经名存实亡了
And then the Xinhai Revolution.
后来辛亥革命
Sun Yatsen overthrew the imperial regime and founded a republic.
孙中山推翻帝制建立了共和国
But what is a republic?
但是什么是共和呀
Mr. Sun Yatsen has also been seeking an answer.
中山先生也在苦苦求索
Our compariots even less able to come to agreement
国人更是莫袁一是
each of us with our own opinions.
各取所需 自说自话
We anti-monarchists, Republicans who have
我们这些反帝制 求共和
gone through fire and water
出生入死几十年的人
now must return to being docile subjects of an emperor.
现在倒要回去当皇帝的顺民了
Is history playing a joke on us?
是历史在跟我们开玩笑吗
So today I just want to ask
所以今天我就想问问
This most critical moment in 3000 years
这三千年未遇之大变局
This greatest enemy in 3000 years
三千年未遇之大强政
What does it really refer to?
到底指的是什么
Mr. Chen's words are just so insightful.
陈先生讲话就是有见地
Hit the nail on the head with a single sentence.
一句话就说到点子上了
That's right.
对
What insight?
什么有见地
It's just banal truisms.
就是一些老生常谈的话
I think his glib and exaggerated ways
我就看他那夸夸其谈的样子
is just the same as before.
还是跟以前一点没变
He only boasts and causes trouble
就知道卖嘴惹事
without taking any responsibility.
一点担当都没有
As I see it
依我所看
the crisis is the collapse of the imperial regime
变局指的就是帝制的崩溃
the powerful enemy refers to the Western Powers, right?
强敌指的就是西方列强吧
Crises - China has experienced many.
变局 中国经历的多了
From Qin Shihuang to Puyi
从秦始皇到小宣统
There has been tens of dynastic changes
改朝换代几十次
But in the end it's still
到头来还不是
exchanging one autocracy for another.
专制体制的循环吗
China has also faced many strong enemies
强敌中国也经历的多了
Since ancient times
古往今来
how many enemies have battled to the Central Plains?
有多少强敌打到了中原
And the result?
结果呢
Not only did our China not wither away
我泱泱中华不仅没有消亡
but like a rolling snowball grow bigger and bigger.
反而像滚雪球一样的越滚越大
5000 years of Chinese Civilization
中华文明五千年
That is the advantage left to us by our ancestors.
这是老祖宗留给我们的优势
So we have the self-confidence.
所以 我们有这个自信
Zhongfu, what you've spoken of is history.
仲甫啊 你说的这些个都是历史
Now is no longer the past.
现在今非昔比了
Exactly.
没错
The Opium War broke this pattern.
鸦片战争打破了这个格局
This time it is really different.
这一次真的不同
This time we are facing
这一次我们遇到的
a truly unprecedented enemy.
真的是前所未有的强敌
This great enemy
这个强敌
is not only militarily strong
不光强在武力上
but more importantly, strong
更重要的
in terms of ideology and theory.
他是强在思想上和理念上
Not only do they have
他们不仅有
advanced weaponry as a result of industrial production
工业时代所产生的先进武器
They also have advanced ideological systems
他们还有资本时代所产生的
as a result of capitalism.
先进理念和先进的体制
Compared to them
在他们面前
our system is backwards.
我们的制度落后了
Our thoughts are also backwards.
我们的思想也落后了
In short, our people are backwards.
一句话 我们的人落后了
For our great Chinese civilization,
这是我们决决中华
in thousands of years, this is the first time.
几千年文明史上的第一次
Right?
对吗
Therefore our conclusion is
所以我的结论是
in order to transform China,
改造中国
we must first transform the minds of Chinese people
首先要改造中国人的思想
Improve the Suzhi of Chinese people
提高中国人的素质
In order to recover China's former splendour
要想光复中华昔日之辉煌
the most urgent need is
当务之急的
to bring up a new generation of people.
要造就一代新人
Brother Zhong Fu is right.
仲甫兄说得好啊
An original insight.
独具匠心哪
It is true that a new generation
的确开民智造新人
is fundamental for national rejuvenation.
是民族复兴的根本大计
But this is too difficult.
但这事太难了
It can't be accomplished overnight.
不是一朝一夕能完成的
True. This requires a long process
确实 这需要很长一个过程
that can't seek instant returns
不能急功近利
but we also can't hesitate and dither.
我们也不能彷徨徘徊
If we have inborn talent
天生我材
to be afraid to use it is a dereliction of duty
不敢担当就是失职
and leave a legacy of misfortune.
就会遗祸子孙
The likes of us cannot be
我等绝不能做
spectators looking on from the sidelines.
作壁上观的局外人吧
To be concerned, to take on the work.
操大心 办大事
Not be a turtle retracting its head into its shell.
不当缩头乌龟
That is our responsibility.
这是我等的责任
Well said, Zhong Fu.
仲甫 说得好啊
What should we do?
我们该怎么做
First, theoretical basics.
一 思想启蒙
Second, transformation of society.
二 改造社会
Of the multitude of things
悠悠万事 千头万绪
these two are the most important.
唯此两项为大
Zhong Fu,
仲甫啊
there are all kinds of foreign ideologies
那外国人那思想是五花八门哪
and all kinds of thinking.
制度也是五花八门哪
Which one is suitable for our country?
哪一个适合我们国家
Good question!
问得好
In terms advanced western ideologies and institutions,
对西洋先进的思想和制度
we must be discriminating;
我们必须要辨析
we must find the most key
我们要找到最核心
the most universal, the most practical
最普遍 最实用的东西
to arm our youth.
来武装我们的青年
I've been probing this question for many years
这个问题 我探索多年
and have found a clear conclusion
已经找到了明确的结论
which I will soon make known to the world.
不久我会昭告天下
That's why this time I've returned to China
所以此次归国
to establish a magazine
我是想创办一份杂志
that will serve as a rallying cry
作为唤醒国人政治的觉悟的
for the political and ethical awakening of the nation!
和伦理的党悟的号角
I pledge to you all
我向各位保证
that if I run the magazine for ten years
让我办十年杂志
the whole country will change its thinking!
全国思想都会为之改观
Well said! Good!
说得太好了
Good.
好
Everyone.
各位
Each generation has their duty.
一代人有一代人的责任
Our generation's duty is to
我们这些人的责任
is to run this magazine
就是要通过办杂志
in order to identify, select and validate
辨析 选择和验证出
one of the most advanced theories of contemporary thought
一种当代最先进的思想理论
as a means of transforming China's youth
作为改造中国青年
and transforming society
和改造社会的指导思想
to explore a way to revitalise China.
来探索出一条振兴中华的道路
Menzou, time to eat!
孟邹 该开饭了吧
Yes, yes, yes. In the house, please. In the house, please. Come on.
对对对 屋里请屋里请 来
Okay, let's eat. Let's eat.
好 开饭了 开饭了
In the house please, in the house.
屋里请屋里请
Brother Zhong Fu.
仲甫兄啊
What an enlightening experience!
简直是醍醐灌项啊
From now on, you will be our commander-in-chief
以后啊 你就是我们的总司令
and we will listen to you.
听你的
Serve, serve, serve.
上菜 上菜 上菜
Quick, Huzi, bring the tray over here.
快 虎子 把托盘拿过来
Yes, ma'am.
好嘞
Lotus leaf hooves.
荷叶黄牛蹄
Come, Qiaonian.
来 乔年
This one. Bring it over to your father.
这个呀 你给你爹端过去啊
Okay.
好
Huzi, quick.
虎子 快
Lotus leaf hooves.
荷叶黄牛蹄
Quick, Huzi, bring it over.
快 虎子 拿过去
The first thing I propose
这个首先我提议啊
is that we drink to the wonderful opinions
为网才大家精彩的各抒已见
we just exchanged with one another.
我们先干他一杯
Come!
来
Not bad.
不错
Fragrant.
香啊
Menzou,
孟邹啊
just these few dishes?
就这么几个菜呀
Of course not.
当然不是了
The dishes have to be served one by one.
这个菜得一道一道上
A good dish is worth the wait.
好菜不怕晚嘛
Don't you be worried.
着什么急你这是
The most substantial dish today
今天最硬的菜
is a staple dish of my hometown Jixi, Anhui.
是我的安徽绩溪老家的当家菜
Lotus leaf hooves.
荷叶黄牛蹄
Great.
挺好啊
Even in Anhui-style restaurants
这个菜在外边的徽菜馆里
you won't see this dish
你是见不到的
because the ingredients
因为这个原料呵
are too hard to get.
实在是太难搞了
It's from entirely purebred
是一水的纯种
oxen that's three and a half years old
三岁半的小黄牛蹄子
A secret recipe. Wrapped in lotus leaf.
秘方制成 荷叶包裹
Tastes exquisite.
味美色香啊
The best of Anhui cuisine.
是徽菜中的极品
One for each, today.
今天每人一个
Everyone has a share.
大家都有份
One for each!
一人一只
Seven people, seven hooves.
七个人七只牛蹄
That's two head of oxen.
那可是两头黄牛
Right.
对呀
That's one substantial dish.
这可真是一道硬菜
What do you think, Zhong Fu? Am I stingy?
怎么样啊仲甫 我抠门吗
Let's taste it first.
尝了再说吧
Come on. Lotus wrapped hooves.
来来来 荷叶黄牛蹄
Here it comes.
走菜喽
Quick, Qiaonian, you go first.
快 乔年 你在前面
Huzi, follow.
虎子 跟上
Great!
好
Look, here it comes.
你看 端上来了啊
Qiaonian, how is it you?
乔年 怎么是你呀
Let me introduce everyone.
我给大家介绍一下啊
This is Zhongfu's second son, Qiaonian.
这就是仲甫的二公子 乔年
Wow. He's grown up!
都长这么大了
What a talented young man.
小伙子一表人才
A grown up boy.
大小伙子呀
Qiaonian, your old man has come back.
乔年 你家老子回来了
Come, go see your father.
来 见过你爹
I'll have one first.
来 我先来一个
There's one for everyone.
每人都有
Good good good.
好好好
One per person.
每人一个
Come, I give to you.
来来 给 您的
This is a token of respect for his father.
这是人家孝敬他爹的
Not bad, not bad, not bad.
不错不错不错
Qiaonian brought it up especially for you.
乔年专门给你端上来的
Grab a bite!
抓紧吃
A son's filial piety to his old father.
儿子孝敬老子的
Come, come, come.
来来来
This big yellow cow's hoof.
这大黄牛蹄子
What's... what's going on here?
这这 怎么回事
I don't know!
我不知道啊
Mr. Chen, don't be angry. Mrs. Chen, don't be angry.
陈先生息怒 陈太太息怒
It's all my fault. My fault!
这都是我的错 我的错
Sister-in-law, it's not your fault.
嫂子 不是你的错
Qiaonian.
乔年
What's going on?
怎么回事
You shouldn't be the only one who did it.
不应该只是你一个人干的吧
Where are your associates?
你的同伙呢
Bring him here.
让他出来
Chen Yannian, come out!
陈延年 出来
I'm the mastermind of this.
这事我是主谋
Take it out on me if you're angry.
你们有气冲我撒
Yannian, how old are you?
延年 你多大了
Are you still a child?
你还是孩子吗
You are an adult!
你是成年人
How could you do such a ridiculous thing?
怎么能干出这么荒谬的事情
Even if you have a problem with your old man,
你即便对你们老子有意见
you can't treat him like this!
也不能这样对待他
Do you know what you call this?
你知道你这样做叫什么吗
This is called treason!
叫大逆不道
This would be frowned upon in our home town!
这在我们家乡要遭到唾骂
Heaven condemns you!
遭天谴的你
Sorry, Uncle Wang, Aunt Wang.
对不起汪伯伯 汪伯母
I've put you in a difficult position.
让你们为难了
I do this today,
今天我这么做
not because of him, Chen Duxiu,
不是因为他陈独秀
who didn't take enough care of my mother and us two brothers.
对我母亲和我们兄弟俩照顾不够
In Anqing,
我们在安庆
we were not rich.
日子虽然不富裕
But at least the family has some property,
但是家里好歹有一些产业
enough for our family to live on.
足够我们一家人生活了
Since he doesn't care about us,
既然他不管我们
we won't beg him again.
我们也不会再央求他
We're doing this today
我们今天这么做
for the sake of our suffering family
就是为了替我们受苦的家人
and for
和因为他
our cousin Chen Yongnian, who has been tortured because of him,
才受尽了酷刑的堂兄陈永年
to teach him a lesson.
来教训他陈独秀的
To speak of treason,
要说大逆不道
Chen Duxiu is the one who is really
他陈独秀才是个真正
a treacherous hypocrite.
大逆不道的伪君子
Yannian, you're going too far!
延年 你这话可就太过分了
Don't talk about your father like that!
不许这么说你爹
You shut up!
你给我闭嘴
Let him speak.
让他说
Alright.
好
Today, in front of all my uncles and aunts,
我今天就当着各位叔叔伯伯的面
I'm going to reveal the shame of our Chen family.
把我们陈家这些家丑亮出来
Everyone please judge.
请大家评判
Last autumn,
前年秋
after the failure of the Second Revolution in Anqing,
安庆二次革命失败后
Chen Duxiu himself abandons his family and flees,
陈独秀自己弃家而逃
knowing the danger,
明知危险
but still left his sick grandmother
仍然置生 病的奶奶
and our mother and son behind.
和我们母子的死活于不顾
Ni Xichong sent his men to raid our house.
倪嗣冲派人抄了我们家
My sister, Yuying, sacrificed her life to block the front hall
我妹妹玉莹拼死挡在前堂
covering me and Qiaonian to jump out of the window.
掩护我和乔年跳窗逃命
Cousin Chen Yongnian
堂兄陈永年
who protected his younger brother Chen Zhannian
为了保护弟弟陈讼年
was arrested for pretending to be me,
冒充是我被捕
and was tortured to death.
受尽了严刑拷打
Grandfather, who died after a long illness, was still at home
之前病逝的爷爷 尚暂厝在家
Grandmother is bedridden.
奶奶又卧病在床
The family rushed to Shanghai
族人赶到上海
to find Chen Duxiu,
找到他陈独秀
asking him to return for his father's funeral.
请他回去为父亲送终
But he was greedy for life and death.
但是他贪生怕死
Not only did he not go back to do his filial duty,
非但不回去尽孝
but he instead persuaded the family
反过来还劝说族人
to wait for a few years.
说这事过几年再说
In the eyes of others,
在别人的眼里
Chen Duxiu is a great hero of righteousness.
他陈独秀是个义薄云天的大英雄
But does anyone know,
但是有谁知道
that this is the great hero before you?
就是你们限前的这位大英雄
He lived for himself
他为了自己苟活
and put the lives of his parents at risk.
竟然置父母的死活于不顾
That's what's so treacherous.
这才是大逆不道
You shut up!
你给我闭嘴
Yannian!
延年
You have wronged your father by saying so!
你这么说可是冤枉你父亲了
After the Second Revolution,
二次革命之后
Your father risked his life to persuade Gong Zhenpeng's troops in Wuhu
你父亲冒死去芜湖龚振鹏部
to return to Anqing to fight Yuan.
劝说他起兵回安庆讨袁
However,
可是
this Gong Zhenpeng arrested your father.
这龚振鹏把你父亲抓起来了
The notice to be executed was posted.
枪毙的告示都贴出来了
A matter of life and death,
生死关头
your father
你父亲可是
didn't even frown!
连眉头都没有皱一下啊
It was Liu Shuya who saved him later.
后来还是刘叔雅救了他
He died in Shanghai.
他亡命上海
He was the most wanted man at the time.
那可是通缉的头号要犯
A reward of one thousand yuan was offered.
悬赏大洋一干元
At that time,
那个时候
how could he possibly go back to Anqing?
他怎么可能回得了安庆啊
Yannian. Do you know
延年 你知道吗
the people who came to Shanghai to find your father?
到上海来找你父亲的族人
They were sent by Ni Xichong.
那是倪嗣冲派来的
It was a trap!
这是个圈套啊
Your father risked his life to return for a funeral
当时你父亲冒死想回去送葬
but we stopped him.
是我们生把他给拦下来了
He didn't go back.
他没回去
In those days,
那些日子
he pointed to the picture of Ni Xichong every day and said
他天天指着倪嗣冲的那个照片说
he wanted to eat his own flesh!
恨不得肉食其人
But what you said about your father
可是你这样说你们的父亲
is not fair to him.
那委屈他了
Then we were not wronged!
那我们就不委屈
My grandfather, my grandmother,
我爷爷 我奶奶
my mother, my cousin,
我妈 我堂兄
they were not wronged!
他们就不委屈
Was he wronged? Was he aggrieved?
他受没受铭枉 委不委屈
It's not for us to judge.
这事不由我们评说
Today, this matter
今天这个事
is not a prank
不是一场恶作剧
because he doesn't deserve to eat this dish.
因为他不配吃这个菜
We did this today
我们今天这么做
as a way to explain to the family
也算是给家里人一个交代
From now on, we clear our grudges,
从今往后我们恩怨两清
not cross each other's paths,
井水不犯河水
and go our separate ways.
各走各的路
If you uncles and uncles feel
如果各位叔叔伯伯觉得
that this is a prank
这是一场恶作剧的话
then we apologise to everyone
那我们向大家道歉
for scaring our uncles and aunts.
把叔叔伯伯吓着了
Aunt, we are sorry for your loss.
姨妈 我们对不住您
We've scared you too.
把您也给吓着了
It was not our intention.
这不是我俩的本意
We don't hold a grudge against you.
我们不记恨您
Please forgive us.
请您原谅
Yannian!
延年
Yannian! Yannian!
延年 延年
By the way,
顺便说一句
we didn't come to Shanghai to join you.
我们来上海不是来投奔你的
Let me put it to you this way,
我这么跟你说吧
we came
我们是看了
after we read the work-study initiative.
留法勤工俭学倡议书后
We decided to come to Shanghai to study French
才决定来上海学习法文
and go to France to work and study.
准备去法国勤工俭学的
We'll make our own way,
我们今后的路我们自己走
don't worry about it.
用不着你操心
Yannian! Qiaonian!
延年 乔年
Listen to me, Yannian!
延年乔年听我说呀 延年
This... I... I... you say, you say...
这 我我 你说你说
Well, those are my sons.
好 是我儿子
Zhong Fu, how can you laugh at that?
仲甫 这亏你还笑得出来
Both sons have disowned you.
俩儿子都不认你了
I, Chen Duxiu, have two such wonderful sons.
我陈独秀有两个如此优秀的儿子
Why can't I laugh?
为什么不能笑啊
I didn't get to give my parents a final send-off,
我没能给父母送终
I deserve to die for that.
自是罪该万死
The fact that they remembered to blame me
他们记怪我
shows that they are humane people.
说明他们是懂仁义的人啊
The fact that they are willing to work hard rather than rely on me
他们宁肯吃苦打工也不依赖我
shows that they are self-reliant and self-sufficient people.
说明他们是自立自强的人
In such a fragile world,
如此刮世
aren't these two qualities
能有这两种品质
to be congratulated?
难道不可喜可贺吗
Zhong Fu, you haven't said a word.
仲甫 你刚才一直没说话
I'm still trying to figure out how to comfort you.
我这还琢磨怎么来安慰你呢
You, on the contrary, he's praising his son.
你倒 他倒夸起他儿子来了
But what he said,
不过这样说
is a relief to us all.
我们大家可就放心了啊
It is.
就是
But Zhong Fu,
不过仲甫啊
I've just been watching your two boys,
我刚才一直在观察你这俩小子
they're not normal.
真不是一般人
They will be great men in the future.
将来呀 必成大器
That's right!
没错
These two children have high ambitions!
这两个孩子真是志存高远哪
Brother Mengzou.
孟邹兄
Apologies to you.
向你道歉
You're not stingy
你不抠门
with your lotus leaf and yellow cow's trotters.
荷叶黄牛蹄 下了血本
I accept, I accept.
我接受我接受
Let's switch!
咱俩换一下
You're dirty. You eat this.
你这脏了 你吃这个
No, no, no.
不用 不用
Didn't you hear what my son said?
没听我儿子说吗
I don't deserve to eat this dish.
我不配吃这道菜
There are other dishes here.
别的菜也可以吃
So, so, so, let's do it!
那那那 咱们来吧
Come on!
来吧
Come, come, come!
来 来来来
Please, please!
请 请 请
Have a drink!
喝点酒
[Waseda University dormitory, Japan]
[日本早稻田大学宿舍]
[Li Dazhao, styled Shou Chang, student at Waseda University]
[李大钊 字 守常 日本早稻田大学学生]
In 1915,
一九一五年
the twenty-six-year-old Li Dazhao
二十六岁的李大钊
wrote the article "Misanthropy and Self-awareness"
写下了《厌世心与自觉心》一文
against Chen Duxiu's "Patriotism and Self-consciousness",
向陈独秀的《爱国心与自觉心》
as challenge.
发起挑战
With a positive and optimistic attitude,
他以积极乐观的态度
he urged the nation to rise
呼吁国人振奋起来
and join the movement against Yuan.
踊跃投身于倒袁运动
Improving the spirit of nationalism
改进立国之精神
and enouraging patriotism;
求一可爱之国家而爱之
by this time, Li Dazhao
此时的李大钊
had become
已经成为一名
a thoroughgoing anti-feudal activist.
彻底的反封建斗十
Shou Chang.
守常
What are you doing?
做什么呢你
You scared the hell out of me.
吓我一跳
Mr. Xing Yan, what brings you here?
行严先生 您怎么来了
Have a seat!
快请坐
I'm going back home, just wanted to see you.
我就要回国了 过来看看你
Please sit!
您坐
What's the matter? What's the panic?
怎么了这是 这么慌乱
Did something happen?
发生什么事了吗
I may have recently become
我可能最近
a thorn in the side
变成了某些日本学生的
of some Japanese students.
眼中钉和肉中刺了
[Zhang Tuzhao, styled Xing Yan, revolutionary exiled to Japan]
[章土钊 字 行严 流亡日本革命者]
They often use the pretext of supervising my classes
他们经常借着督我上课的名义
to pick fights,
过来挑事
destroying my manuscripts.
毁我稿子
So when I hear a knock at the door,
所以眼下我听见敲门声的
my first thought was to hide the manuscript.
第一反应就是藏稿子
You attend a variety of events and make a lot of appearances,
你参加各种活动 出面又较多
it is inevitable that you will be watched.
被人盯上是难免的
Shou Chang.
守常啊
I've heard the school has a lot to say about you.
我听说学校对你意见很大
Japanese universities are very strict in their administration.
日本的大学管理非常严格
You need to be careful.
你可得注意了
[Gan Yihao, student at Waseda University]
[高一涵 日本早稻田大学学生]
You have to find
你得找到
a way to make the most of both your studies and the revolution.
学业和革命两不误的路子
I heard you. I am organizing
最听呢我正在筹办
the Chinese Students Association in Japan.
中国留日学生总会
And I'm planning to talk to Yihan
而且我还打算跟一涵
to start a magazine called "Minyi" (Rule of people's will)
办一本叫《民彝》的杂志
as a publication of the association.
作为留日总会的刊物
Inspired by the "Jiayin",
受《甲寅》的启发
the "Minyi" also opposes
《民彝》也反对
and resists Yuan Shikai's authoritarian politics
和抵御袁世凯的专制政治
by commenting and discussing the current situation,
并希望通过评论和探讨时局
to foster a modern civilization
灌输近世文明
and promote the awakening of the people.
和促进民众觉醒
It did make me miss a lot of classes,
这让我确实耽误了不少课程
but the revolutionary situation at the moment
但是眼下革命形势
is in full swing.
正是激烈的时候
I had a really hard time choosing.
我真的很难选择
This is not acceptable.
这样可不行
In my opinion,
我的观点啊
academics are also the essence of the revolution.
学业也是革命的本钱
Now that you are in the door,
既然进了这个门槛
you must get your diploma.
就一定要把文凭拿到
Otherwise, it'll be a shame.
要不然多可惜
In fact, the usual is doing quite well.
其实 守常做得算是不错了
In 11 subjects last school year,
上学年十一门课
he scored 736 points.
他是考了七百三十六分嘛
In politics and economics,
在他们政治经济学系
out of 106 students
一百零六名学生当中
he ranked in the top 40.
也是排在前四十位
Because he's never had a high school education
因为他没有读过预科
and went straight to undergraduate school,
他直接进的本科
that's a good grade, it's not bad.
这个成绩 算是不错
Just third place, it's a shame.
只是丙等 惭愧
Third place is really not bad.
丙等很不错了
You're good and you're willing to work hard.
你底子好 又肯吃苦
Academics are not a problem for you.
学业对你来说不是问题
Compliance with school rules is your problem.
遵守校规是你的问题
I'm really at a bit of a loss now.
我现在真的是有点茫然
What is more important, the revolution or school?
革命和上学到底孰轻孰重
It's really hard for me to choose.
真的让我很难取舍
You put yourself out on a hot day,
大热天的你把自己
locked up in your dorm room studying.
关在宿舍里边学习
That means you know the difference.
说明你分得很清楚嘛
What are you writing?
在写什么呢
I had an appointment with Mr. Zhongfu for a debate
我和仲甫先生约好了辩论的
and I wrote a piece on "Misanthropy and Self-awareness"
我写了一篇《厌世心与自觉心》
in which he refuted his arguments.
他驳他的观点
Help me take a look
您帮有我看看
Alright!
行啊
In this, you are really above Zhong Fu in enthusiasm.
你这算是真的跟仲甫较上劲了
Speak.
说说
First of all, I feel
首先 我 认为
the thing Mr. Zhong Fu is advocating is
仲 先生 提倡 的 那个
to have a country, not for happiness.
有 国家 不 为 喜
It's an argument that is pessimistic and misanthropic.
是 一 种 世 误 国
What is consciousness?
何 为 自觉
Strive unremittingly to establish a new country.
自 强 不 地 创立 一 个 新 的 国家
We can't, for the reason this country is not lovable,
我 们 不 能 因为 这 个 国家 不 可 爱 了
just stop loving the country
就 不 爱国 了
Even more we can not, just because we
更 不 能 因为 我 们
didn't enjoy this country's love,
没有 到 这 个 国家 的
I approve this point of view of yours.
我 你 这 个 观点
But I feel this conscious heart of Zhong Fu's,
可 是 我 党 仲 的 这 个 自觉 心 呢
must have a deeper meaning.
应 该 有 更 深层 次 的 含义
I heard right now he's not putting a foot outside,
我 听 说 他 现在 是 足 不 出 户
shutting his head in to find China a prescription.
着 给 中 国 找 药方 呢
You watch. Maybe one day
你 看 着 没准 一 天
this can really have him give out
的 能 让 他 放出 一 个
a thunderbolt from the sky.
惊天 炸 雷 来
Actually, the debate between Mr. Zhong Fu and I
人 和 人
was also want to push him to make a move.
。 也 是 想 他 出 招
I really want to see his muddled interior
我 的 看 看 他 的
in the end, to see what medicine he is selling.
到 底 卖 的 什么 药
Alright. How about this.
好 那 就 这 样
This piece of writing,
这 篇 文章 呢
send it to this period's "Jiayin".
就 发 这 一 期 的 《 甲 寅 》
Arrange it tomorrow
了 明天 就 发
and see if this Chen Zhong Fu will be provoked or not.
看 看 这 个 陈 仲 甫 接 不 接 招
Okay.
好
Brother Meng Zou. Sit.
兄
Coming to find me, what is it for?
来 找 我 到 底 什么 事 啊
To be honest,
实 不 相
I come to take refuge.
《 我 是 来 避难 的
Workers of the printing house
4 印 的 工人
already blocked up the front door of my house.
到 我 家 门 了
Before, didn't you already find investors?
之 前 不 是 找到 投资 人 了 吗
Before, the 300 silver dollars
之 前 那 三 百 大 洋
handle procedures, rent the building, rent machines,
办 续 租房 子 租 机 器
we were unable to have any money left.
也 剩 不 了 几 个 钱 了
It... You see... It's just this time,
它 它你看偏 偏偏这个时候
the capitalists have offered to withdraw their investment,
资方提出来要撤资
and I don't know for what reason.
也 不 知道 什么 原因
I tried my best to persuade, no results.
我 好 说 说 的 没有 效果
With no better option, I go all over the place to find money.
只 好 四 处 去 找 钱
I scrape for gold with a thin Buddha face to search for help.
我 是 刮 金 佛 面 细 搜 求
Didn't gain anything.
4 有 何 收获
Then right now how much are you short of.
那 现在 还 缺 多 少 啊
The initial number
创刊 号
added to next month's 200 silver dollars of monthly loan repayment.
加 上 下 月 两 百 大 洋 的 月 供
The very least is 400 silver dollars
至 少 也 得 四 百 大 洋
to be able to maintain until the next cycle.
才能 撑 到 下 一 期
You say, my little publishing house
你 说 我 这 个 小 书社
still needs allowance to supplement "Jiayin".
还 要 贴补 《 甲 寅 》
No matter what I do, I can't get the money.
我 无 论 如 何 我 不 出
If next period I still can't find money,
如 果 下 一 期 再 找 不 到 钱
I'm afraid that your magazine will also prematurely end.
恐怕 你 这 本 杂志 也 要 天 折 了
You say, the inside of this home,
你 说 这 家 里 边
if something like antiques are passed down,
要 是 传 下 来 一 些 什 么 古玩 啊
calligraphy and painting and what not,
字画 啊 什 么 的
then at this crucial point in time
那 这 关键 的 候
you can answer your worries.
也 能 应 上 急 呀
Mengzou. Here, drink tea.
邹 来 喝 茶
Thank you.
谢谢
In a moment, have a meal here.
一 会 儿 在 家 里 吃饭
Junman.
君 曼
Would you please go and run...
麻烦你去跑一趟
run to help me get Chen Zishou, Chen Zipei,
去 帮 有 我 把 陈 子 寿 陈 子 沛
the two brothers to come here.
两 个 兄弟 请 来
For what reason?
什么 由 头 啊
Just say I have to find him for an urgent matter.
你 就 说 我 有 急事 找 他
Quickly go.
快 去
Okay I know now.
好 我 、
Alright.
行 了
Come. Drink tea.
来 喝 茶
Don't look miserable now.
别 苦 脸 的 了
Listen to me talk about that.
你 听 我 呵 说 说 那个
The subject of our of our first issue
我 们 创刊 的 主题
is to tell the youth,
是 告诉 青年
at this moment,
在 当下
should be what kind of new generation.
应 该 做 一 种 什么 样 的 新 人
I feel there are 6 criterion.
我 觉得 有 六 条 标准
The first one...
第 一 条
Stop, stop.
打住 打住 啊
I don't have even the slightest doubt of your brilliant thinking,
我 丝毫 不 怀疑 你 思想 的 光芒
but we have no money, no silver.
可 是 没有 钱 啊 没有 银子
Your even greater brilliance, you can't put it out.
你 再 大 的 光芒 你 放 不 出 来
Stop being miserable!
你 别 苦 脸 的
Listen to me!
I 你 听 我 说 呀
Wait.
得 、
Wait, wait, wait.
” 得 得 得
Right now, I really have no mood to listen.
我 现在 实在 是 真 的 没 心 情 听
Let me calm down a bit.
人
You, go write your things.
你 呢 的 啊 、。
Write your things.
呢 就 去 写 你 的
I'll be responsible for the money situation.
钱 的 事 我 负责
Be steady alright?
你 踏 踏实 实 的 行 吗
Look, right now it's 3:30.
你 看 现在 三 点 半
At 4 O'clock, the money situation will be handled.
四 点 钟 钱 这 事 一 定 能 解决
Listen to me, the 6 criterion.
听 我 说 六 条 标准
First one,
第 一 条
one must be independent and not a slave.
自主 的 而 非 隶 的
The so-called aggressive rather than the retreating.
所谓进取的 而非退隐的
What is called to overcome all obstacles as well as to go forward.
所 谓 排除 万 难 而 前 行
Thus, life's duty...
人 生 之 天 职
Okay I know whatever I'm going to say now.
好 吧 我 知道 我 现在 说 什么
It won't enter your ears.
你 也 听 不 进去
Then, you come. Help me grind ink.
那 你 来 帮 有 我 研
What do you want now?
你 又 干什么 呀
I want you to grind ink.
我 让 你 研 研
I want to write.
我 要 写字
Hurry up!
快 点
My characters
我 的 字
were practiced when I was depressed in the time of my exile.
” 是 在 流亡 期 间 苦 时 练 的
Crooked sevens twisty eights. Looks like it's crying out a grievance.
七 扭 八 像 是 在
So I call it bitter form.
故 自 称 体喊
Not easily taken out to show people.
不 轻易 拿 出 去 示人
this brother Mengzou took a lot of trouble so far for me.
这 个 孟 兄 为 我 费心 至 此
I can't keep maintaining my personal integrity during chaotic times.
我 也 不 能 再 其 身 了
I am already in a desperate situation,
你 还 有 闲 心 写字
You are thinking a way out is a way out.
你 是 想 一 出 是 一 出 啊 你
Didn't I already say,
我 不 说 了 吗
this money situation, I'll deal with it.
这 钱 的 事 我 来 管 呵
Why do you still not believe me?
你 怎么 还 不 信 我 呀
You... don't manage the household, you don't know firewood and rice are expensive?
你 呀 是 不 当家 不 知道 柴 米 贵
With this talking,
这 说 着 说 着
I suddenly thought of 3 years ago.
我 突然 想起 三 年 前 来 了
At that time you took up post as Anhui province's Bai Wenyu's secretary-general,
那 时 候 你 任 安 徽 柏 文 的 秘书 长
I brought silver to meet you.
我 带 着 大 洋 去 见 你
to seek a hometown‘s
想 谋 个 家 乡 的 “
county head commissioner's position to sit on.
一 个 县 长 的 位 置 坐
At that time, the content of your conversation had me awaken.
当时 你 的 一 席 话 让 我 觉醒 了
You say at the start of this year
你 说 这 年 头
being a government official is the most dangerous most short-lived position.
当 官 是 最 高 危 最 短命 的 职业
Saying being done for means being done for.
那 说 完蛋 就 完蛋
You say you have money.
钱
Why didn't you open a publishing house at Shanghai?
你 还 不 如 到 上 海 去 开 一 个 书社
Firstly... it can be because of your home.
一 来 呢 可 以 为 家 里
Plan a smooth and steady life,
谋 得 一 个 安稳 的 生活
you can collect funds for the revolution.
也 可 以 为 革命 筹集 一 些 资金
At that time, I listened to you. There's still today.
我 当时 听 你 的 了 才 有 今天
I listened to you.
你 的 了
Do you still remember?
你 还 记得
Can life saving words still be forgotten?
救命 的 话 能 忘 吗
What you say is also right.
你 说 也 对
That year, those corrupt officials' deaths
当年 全 死 的
is an runaway escape.
是逃的逃啊
This is really similar to that book of Victor Hugo's
这 真 像 是 果 写 的 那 部 书
"Les Miserables"
《 世界 》
Fortunately, you awakener of Les Miserables
幸 得 你 这 惨 世界 的 党 醒 者 啊
still have us
这 民 的 杂志
Zhong Fu.
仲
Mr Zishou and Mr Zipei have arrived.
子 寿 子 沛 先生 来 了
This way.
请
Brother Mengzou.
孟
Brother Zhong Fu.
仲 甫 兄
Then, you gentlemen have a chat first.
那 你 们 先 聊
Good!
好
Brother Zhong Fu.
仲 甫 兄
Why have you thought of us brothers today
怎么 今天 想起 我 们 兄弟 了
Calling us over here, what instructions do you have?
把 我 们 叫 过 来 有 什么 只
I remember last time we had a gathering.
我 记得 上 次 我 们 相聚
Brother said I was petty.
子 寿 兄 说 我 小 气
Didn't let you guys write, right?
不 给 你 们 写字 是 吧
It turns out Brother Zhong Fu had us two brothers come
敢 情 仲 甫 兄 让 我 们 兄弟 二 人 前 来
to settle accounts from last autumn.
是 想 秋 后 算账 吧
I don't dare.
不 敢 不 敢 不
Today, I invite you guys over.
我 今天 请 你 们 来
I want to mend my image in the hearts of the two of you.
是 想 修补 我 在 二 位 心中 的 形象 “
This is my humble writing that was just
这 是 刚刚 出 炉 的 作
the two of you, please, have a laugh.
请 二 位 笑 纳
This is really too good.
这 真是 太 好 了
It's not finished yet
没完 没完 呢
These words of mine, I can't write them wrong.
我 这 字 它 不 能 白 写